Next we talk about a concept called exception propagation that is how our exceptions actually
propagated right.
So before understanding that let's talk about real world analogy I will always take is that
let's say we have a three-story building right and on the top floor there's a person
who is juggling with a ball on a fine Sunday morning right just playing catch up and goes
on to to the story says that once after many attempts the boy on the top floor misses
the ball right what has happened does does the ball directly fall on the ground no it
goes to the second floor on the second floor there's a person who's watering his plants
and misses that ball as well then it goes to to the first door on the first floor there
is a girl who is reading a good novel and again misses the ball and then it goes through
to the ground floor and then is that falls on the ground but not before giving you three chances
to catch it that is the ball right similarly we have exceptions that are propagated that
is for example if you have a good look at this let's say I was not getting this exception
let me comment this see I was not having try catch sorry see one variable one variable
piece of code here right mind break any time and and the problem is we don't know when
what if it would break but we know it's a vulnerability we've not taken care of that now
we'll just run this just have a look at this I want to show you something say and do
numbers 23 nine works fine run this again one two zero zero yeah exception thread name divided
by zero but just have a look at this just zoom into this it says at calculate division
dot divide handle exceptions dot Java 22 that is it was originated from this but then
also tells you handle exception Java 13 that is it was raised from here as well you
might wonder why you might wonder how because the exception came at 22 but which is the
code that it that called it it was the line number 13 which called divide right if you
had never called divide in the first place you would have no probability of this exception
being thrown right that is why when this exception is thrown at that this line in
line number 22 obviously 23 would not even be evaluated let alone executed it immediately
goes out of the method right to the calling method at the line where the call was made
and that is what we call as the stack trace it just prints you the complete status
it originated from 22 but even at 13 that means even this line becomes responsible in
turn it this line becomes vulnerable because if you never call divide there would have
been no exception at all times that means this line also becomes vulnerable and that
is the stack trace right that is how it gets out of the stack right that is how exceptions
are propagated we are getting my point right that is exception propagation in Java
and related concept is now think about it what I will do is see I will go to work and
this is another example I always take a great example to understand how it just works
all of it and how it makes sense I will create a new class let me call it exceptions propagation
or exception propagation and have the mean now you had a method that is let us say white
print charts you are working on project you need to print charts and suddenly the requirement
came in that is at 6 o'clock in the evening at 558 from your team lead that is the requirement
they want the charts to be printed a different way so you are about to leave home but
they said that the deadline is by end of day to day so what will you do the option A is
you will go on dive deep take help online AI you took everything and you will just write
your code but that is going to take a lot of hit and tries and a lot of time and you don't
know whether that would be done by end of day but you remember your team leads words
that is the deadline is today by end of day so the option B is you look online for a solution
that already exists and you find one after searching for 15 20 minutes which has five
star ratings online right and you just they try to call that so how would it work so for
example and this is just an assumption that code that you downloaded from GitHub is like
this and say back age special and there was a class for example class work with or that
is it automatic charts someone has created that with a five star rating online on GitHub
and then there was a major wide make charts takes the index X axis or Y axis and writes
the code here code here to generate charts effective right so we don't know that code right
we just downloaded what we need and we just need to call it so obviously I will just
come in this because you know that in a Java file there can only be one package statement
declaration and it should be the top and that is it so I just come in this just assume
that this code is what you downloaded so how do you call it now from your print charts
you will just say you will obviously import the spatial dot automatic charts class
and they should be public you know that by now and then you just call the method you
just say new automatic charts dot make charts you will take the numbers on runtime but
for now this works 67 97 I will come in this out obviously when you run this so you will
get the charts and you just push this to production and your manager is happy you are happy
you go home and have a good nice sleep and this was just done in one hour or so that's fine
so now after three months of this solution being working the team lead comes to you says
that I got a call from the project manager of my client where we have deployed this application
they say that this code was only absolutely fine for three months thank you very much
for that but suddenly since yesterday we were getting unusual unusual behavior we're getting
an error or something we don't understand but for three months that same code work and that
has left them to wonder what is going on wrong right and after diving into your code for
a couple of hours scratching your heart head you come up on the conclusion there was nothing
wrong with your code nothing wrong because you called print charts from here like this
new exception propagation dot print charts and from print charts you went to make charts
did the solution just fine but after scratching your head for a couple of hours you come
to the conclusion that this is originating from somewhere in that five star code right and turns
out that guy with a five star rating has not taken here of an exception right and turns out that
five star code was not that five star in the first place because this guy hasn't even taken
here I told you as a developer you never know if my code would cause an exception what time
would it cause it but you would always know my code has a piece which is dangerous which is
susceptible to dangers which has a vulnerability to a particular exception exceptions and that's why
you should always take here right but this book has not done it right and you put in a comment on
on there get a repository page and say that you have not taken care of this exception please do
that because it's causing me exception after three months of running this fine we understand it's
a special piece of coding just serves the purpose but it has a problem that might break this code
any time so you have not taken here so this guy goes in and takes care let's try
right and puts this in a tried garage and let's say he's expecting a IO exception
like this and then there's something here with the exception
all right and now you know it would be handled well or obviously you need it to handle it
right here right it should be handled somewhere so pushes the score back to get help you get the
latest update and you push it live to your production the client is happy your manager is happy
your happy as well you can spend your weekend in a piece for me right so this is the first step that
he took right I would still say this guy is a good job at developer but not an excellent one why
because he would have been excellent because if he would have told us that all the taken care of
the exception you don't need to worry about it but you have every right to know your dealing with
potentially your calling potentially dangers why did I say potentially because you would never
know whether the exception would come or not as you saw in this example it came after three months
but when it did it right have right so this guy thinks that anyone calling my code my make
charts has a right to know whether I'm taking care of that or not whether try catch they have a
right to know they are calling possibly potentially dangerous code so I need to make them away
I need to inform them before they call me and how does it make that right happen
then that is a beautiful scenario of inter metal communication when a method talks to another
method the call the method to the calling method that is gives them a warning and how do you do
that with the keyword throws do you put that exception right here as part of the metal signature
at the first line with the keyword throws and remember throws does not mean it is throwing it
throws means it might throw it please take care right now this make charts is communicating to
any method that is calling it in our case that is print charts that is please take care the score
is great fabulous five star but it might break at runtime do not do not depend on me I might take
care or not but you take care and that is where throws comes in and that is where inter
method communication comes in and that is where a rule that I call as the handle or declare
rule comes into picture now what is the handle or declare rule right just make a note there
or just understand this that is if a method is throwing an exception or exceptions as part of their
method signature the calling method also then needs to either handle it or declare it to be
thrown right that is the rule otherwise you will get a compile time error in Java right now
how do you handle it you know this needs to be done in a tri-catch but you have a choice
either handle it or also declare it to be thrown like this exactly all right so you either have a choice
either put this also in a tri-catch but if you think that has already put in a tri-catch
you need to declare it that's the handle or declare rule again I'll just reiterate for you
for emphasis that is if a method that you're calling throws an exception as part of their method
signature your calling method also needs to either handle it by tri-catch or throw it as part
of the method signature with the throws and do you see this you an error now inside main as well
because it says unhindling exception jouled iota iota iu exception why because now the
responsibility comes to main why main is calling a method which is throwing an iu exception
as part of the method signature but remember throws does not mean throw it's throwing it actually
it might please take it now main also needs to take here or handle or declare it to be thrown
right and that is or that is how it works the handle or declare rule how does that work in joule
and on the other hand and this is a beautiful scenario because why because you're warning beforehand
the calling method all right you're calling my code I've done something fabulous but please be
aware this is dealing with potentially dangerous code please take care or declare it to be thrown
right so but now if this method was throwing an exception as part of the method signature that is
let's say null pointer exception and this method does not throw it the calling method now you're
not getting a thump file no matter why because go back to that and what I drew for you on my white
board that is the exception class hierarchy right exception and error and with your subclasses
and that is there are two types of exceptions java checked and unchecked now what I checked what
I checked and what does that have to do with with with the handle of declare rule that is
first what I checked and unchecked that is class exception and its subclasses
excluding class runtime exception and its subclasses are categorized in java as checked exceptions
okay class exception exception and its subclasses excluding runtime exception and its subclasses
are categorized in java is checked exceptions class error and its subclasses including class runtime
exception and its subclasses are classified in java as unchecked exceptions so these are the two types
of exceptions now what do they have to do with what we're discussing handle or declare rule that is
the handle or declare rule only applies on checked exceptions in java it does not apply on unchecked
exceptions that's why you saw when I said throws iu exception as part of a method signature
I did not get an error remain because that sorry I got an error remain with iu exception why
because it is a checked exception it's a subclass of exception but when a method throws an unchecked
exception like point to exception arithmetic exception I would not get an error compile time error
although you can still handle or declare it you have a choice but you not get an error because
the handle or declare rule does not apply on unchecked exceptions I just make it clear for you to
understand all right and why is this classification because unhandled exceptions sorry unchecked
exceptions like null pointer exception or even let's say a stack overflow error when is the
situation when you get stack overflow error when you run out of stack memory let's try you
handle that which I catch what is the best that you can do would you just open up the laptop or
a desktop with your screwdriver and put in more RAM so that the stack memory is reloaded and do
that right so that's why I say you can handle unchecked exceptions in java but even if you do
there is very little you can do right so that's why it's your choice whether you want to handle
unchecked exceptions or what there is something concrete that you can do while handling checked
exceptions that's why we have two types of exceptions in java and that's why the handle or declare
rule does not apply to unchecked exceptions but it only applies to checked exceptions in java